Today we'll be playing with one of the most popular algorithms for character animation in video game.
Hi, I'm Jérôme and today we'll be looking at motion matching for character animation.
It's not a paper per se because it was never published as a paper,
but it has been shown in a lot of different talks and GDC talks and stuff.
And so the first thing that is important in motion matching is that you will have
the future trajectory. You need to predict what your trajectory is. And only when you have your
prediction, what you could do is try to find animations to address that prediction. So you
need to have a stable prediction. You need to know in advance what your character would need
to be able to do. So for this, what I will do, in my case, I will work with the locomotion only
as a first example, and I will use a spring damper model to compute how I want the character to move
and also compute at the same time the futures of where the character would be depending on those.
I really recommend you to read the article from Daniel Alden that explained all the
the mathematics for the spring dampers, the critical spring
damper, and how you could use that for a lot of different
stuff. But in this case, to compute the position of a
character, the velocity and acceleration, and predict where
you want to use it. So really, what I have is these functions,
and that this one is the most important one. You give him a
position at times zero velocity at times zero acceleration at
time zero velocity goal your alpha life so it's how much time it takes for the
spring to do half of the distance and a delta time and it will return the next
position next velocity and next acceleration at that time and that's
a second order differential equation that has been solved so the answer is
correct no matter what is the delta time you give him any time in the future it
would actually have the exact position, velocity, and acceleration you will have in that time.
So that's really powerful for that. So I get my gamepad and I can, well, I have a little function
to create a sphere I can draw. Then I get this function. Basically, I'm computing the
directions I want to move, the velocity I want to have, and the orientations I want to get
to get and you have this so if I play this
now I can take my pad and then I can
so the the black is the current positions where I want to add to my character to be
and the yellows are the predicted position orientations I will have
10 frames in the future, 20 frames in the future, 30 frames in the future, say, one second in the
future there. So basically, and that's perfect. I mean, if I release, you could see that everyone
stops on the same spot. So the prediction is perfect. And you can play with it half time to
get something smoother if you need to, or if you want something faster in interaction. And I've
separate this in position and the same for orientation, I can choose how quickly the
orientation change and that kind of stuff. So that is one of the key
need for the motion matching. You need to make sure that you have something that moves in a
physically plausible way and that's how you predict where you will be. In this case, it's
using spring damper to simulate the accelerations
and velocities and all kinds of stuff you could have.
It could be any other system
if you have something that works for you,
but accurately predict your trajectory.
That's really what is important here.
Now that I have this, I can actually load my character.
I can load a little displacement.
I can load a bunch of animations.
So I will have all the running animation
from the LaFUN database.
And we could see the animations we have here.
So basically, it's the character running in all directions,
stopping, accelerating, going strafing animations,
several animations that get a bunch of motion.
Now, the second thing that is important
when you do motion matching, of course,
if we had the, we have our prediction of trajectory,
we see that we've used velocity and acceleration
and that kind of stuff.
So we have something that is extremely smooth
in the trajectory we generate.
And we will want to match animation
those smooth trajectory. But my animation in this case, you could see that the root of my character
is the projected hips on the ground and orientation. So that is a signal
that oscillates a lot. And basically it's a signal that has a lot of small noises.
And if I tried to match the two, my data will not be perfect.
I mean, I would have something that have a lot of noise and I would try to match that noise.
So what do we need to do is to make sure that we remove the noise we have in the signal coming from the animation itself.
And for this, I would use a filter that I will not try to pronounce because I will probably butcher the name badly,
but I will use an SG filter let's say and what the filter does it if you have a
signal that has a lot of noise into it you will make a window and you will try
to you will slide that window slowly to compute the values and every time inside
of that window you will match a polynomial of degree you choose, but you will basically
fit the polynomial, take the middle value, move forward, fit the polynomial, take the
middle value, move forward, fit the polynomial and so on and so on. What I will do in my
case for this motion I will basically fit a window of 2 seconds and I will fit a polynomial
of degree 4 in the middle of the time for the positions and I will go a little further
and go 65 frames for the rotations but filling a polynomial of degree 5.
So that's how I will smooth the signal.
Now I will do this inside of a function
that I call prepareData, because what you do usually
when you have motion matching that kind of stuff,
is that you would take all your animations
and you would put that inside of what we call a database.
That would be a flat structures
of all your frame of animations.
And so that's what this function does.
It takes an animation.
So the quaternions and position of all the bones
and transition and roots and that stuff.
And I will smooth the signal.
I will realign my animation to the smooth one.
So the smoothed root becomes the root of my animation.
And then I will compute the velocities,
the local velocities of all of my bones
and the local angular velocities of all of my bones.
That would be useful for later at the end,
but at least I have everything in my database.
And so it returns, you know, the animation,
the quaternion, the animation of the quaternions,
the position, the velocities and good velocities.
And then I get the frame range and the frame count.
That will actually allows me to know in my database
what are the range of each of an animations
because I will have all my animations back to back
inside of my database and my frame range
will tell me, well, that was an animation,
that was one animation, that was one animation.
And I will build that database for several animations
and several ranges of animations and I will have one big.
So basically this becomes that database.
database. I get all my animations for everything. So if I display now this, so really displaying
my database, I get this. You can see now that the displacement linked to the character is
now smooth in orientations and positions. I don't have the little association anymore.
Now that we have our database of animation itself,
we could start to think about how we will use
that database to play animations.
So how we will match the frame of animations
to our future trajectory the way we want it.
And for this, what we will do is that we will build
a feature vector.
So we will extract a bunch of features
that we are interested in.
And in the case of the locomotions,
What will be the most interesting stuff for us
will be the hips velocity.
So how is the hips moving?
I'll get the feet position and velocities.
So I will know where my feet are
and how they were moving.
And then I will get the future states
which is sample at 10, 20, or 30 frames in the future
inside of my animation.
and I will sample the position of the character
and the orientation of the character.
So it's really the hips, the feet,
a velocity of the feet,
and then the character positions
and the character orientations.
So that's how I will build my feature vector.
And that's what I would do here.
So basically what I'm doing is that
converting all my animations in global space,
so I will be able to compute the position,
the velocity of my foot and my hips also.
And then I will take my current frame,
so I do it for every frame.
So I take my first frame and I compute,
I take the positions of frame plus one,
plus 10, plus 20, plus 30,
just making sure that I'm actually never going over boundaries.
So, you know, I had several animations back to back.
I don't want to take future positions
that comes from different animations.
I want to have future positions
that only belongs to my current animation.
And once you have all of those,
what you do is that you bring back all the data
as local to the current frame.
So I computed the, I have my frame,
this is frame zero is somewhere here in the world.
I get the features, positions there,
and I take all those positions
and I bring them back into zero, zero, zero
relative to the current frame I'm computing.
And when you have that, you could
start to build your feature vector.
And that will be a big, flat features.
When I will have the velocity of my hips,
the position of my left foot, position of my right foot,
velocity of the feet, and then the future positions,
and the future orientations.
And I do that for every frame.
So it's a, the features becomes a tensor of size,
number of frames, and number of columns,
study three in my case here.
It's all the three points and velocities I have.
And then when I've computed all of these,
we could start to display what it looks like.
So this is what is extracted from
our animation. So what we have is the local informations compared to all the current frames
of where the foot positions are, the foot velocities, the hips velocity, and the future
positions and orientations of the character. And we have that for every frame inside of our database.
And that's basically it. I mean, I've extracted all of data, you know, I've already computed
the future trajectory so we will start to be able to match the future trajectory with the data we
have here. The only issue we have right now is that all of this data has a lot of different
values and sizes you know all the values that are from these points are fairly closed around here
but the one is really far in the features have big values. And what I have is one feature
vector that is basically a vector in 33 dimensions. And I just want to be able to
compute the Euclidean distance when I will be searching for the most similar pose.
I would just do a flat Euclidean distance, but something that will have a lot more importance than
other. And I don't want to have to deal with this because it will be tricky to remember, yeah, maybe
this one has a bigger value, this one has less value, I need to give more importance to this or
to that. So what I would do is that I will normalize my vector. It's something that you always do when
you do machine learnings and all of those stuff, that is you normalize all your value, all of your
values inside of your features. And to normalize them, basically, you take the average, the
mean of all your values, you subtract the mean, so all your values, if they were all
from zero to 20, then you will switch, you will slide your window to be around zero.
And then you divide all the values by the standard deviations. So the goal is to have
for all of your feature to have a mean of zero and a standard deviation of one.
So basically everything now is in the same space, everything has the same
importance and when you try to do an Euclidean distance on the flat vector
like this, it would work. So this is what you do. You take the feature mean, the
feature standard deviations. I need to add a really small error here because I
I have a bunch of values that are zeros everywhere
because I've kept the y position of my trajectories,
they're all zeros.
So I keep the feature mean feature standard deviation.
So you take the features, remove the mean,
divide by the standard deviations
and that give you the normalized feature.
Now that I have this, I basically have something
in which I could do Euclidean distance
to compute the closest vector.
And we can start to have something
that Talou has to play back those animations.
So what I would do is that I would have a player.
And basically what the player does,
it stores the current frame I'm playing
and stores the current position and orientations
of every bones and also of the root of my character.
I don't bother with the rest.
And so when you say go to the next frame, what it does,
it basically here, you know, all my data in my database
is moving in space.
So what you have to do is compute the displacements.
So say that if I want to play frame 10,
I need to know how much it moved from frame 9 to frame 10.
And that's the offsets I want to add to my character.
So I want to compute how much displacement was
inside of animations and to add that to my character.
So I can put my character anywhere I want
and I can let him follow the animation.
So that's what this function does.
Takes the actual animations,
orientations of every bones.
but compute the offsets of the displacements only.
And we come back to this later also, so import this.
And now, if you want to play animations and map,
the only thing you have to do is,
what I was doing before, taking my pad inputs
and knowing what I want to do with my character.
And then I compute the future trajectory.
I compute the future position,
velocity and acceleration of my character.
I do the same for my orientation,
and then I compute the one in 10 frame in the future,
20 frame and 30 frame is the future positions
and orientation.
And I get all basically the same trajectory
I've computed before.
What I'm doing is that bringing back all that info
into local space of my character,
because you know right now my future positions
and my future trajectories are in a world space somewhere
where I want my character to be.
But I want to compute everything relative to my character.
All my data is relative to my character.
So convert that relative to my character.
And then I can build my query vector.
So it's the same.
It has the same size as the feature vector.
So it's 33 dimension.
And the easiest way and the most stable way to do it
in this case is to start from the frame I played.
So I take my feature normalized and I do a copy
of the frame that was played.
Why I'm doing this is because I'm using motion matching
to playback animation.
So I know that last frame I wanted to play that frame.
So that means that I know the feed position, the feed velocity and that kind of stuff of what I wanted to do.
That's the really important thing here. I know that I wanted to play this frame, no matter what happened.
That's the frame I wanted to play. So I expect the character to be in that state.
So I take the feature normalized as a starting point for my query vector.
And then I just change the future trajectory positions
and future trajectory direction.
And I do normalize those values the same way.
So I really use the same feature mean
and feature standard deviation that
was used to normalize the vector in the first place.
And that gives me the query vector.
Now that I have the query vector,
I could just ask which is the frame of animation
that minimize the error between my query vector
and the vectors I have in my feature vector.
And I will not use any acceleration libraries
or algorithm, I just brute force the search
because I have around 20,000 frames in this case.
I can brute force that fairly quickly
Because the only thing you really need to do is compute, as I said, an Euclidean distance.
So I take my feature vectors minus my query vector square root and sum the square.
I don't even need to do the square roots if I only keep the square distance.
It's all fine also.
an arc sort in that big array. So it will tell me which row has the lowest value and that will
give me the best frame. So I pick the best frame. That's the one I want to play. That's the one that
has the smallest error. That's the best score, let's say. Now, the only thing I would do is,
and I would just always pick the best one. The first thing I'm doing is something that happens
a lot when you're doing motion matching that it might find that the best frame is the frame that
was just right before you and then you restart to loop and only play a really small piece of
animation. So just to avoid that going backward one frame I just make sure that it doesn't pick any
I will go in the order of the one it shows and make sure that you don't pick any of the frames that
were in my case less than five frames in the past and that would be way enough for him to never
go back in that weird loop and the other part I'm doing is the opposite I'm making sure that the
frame it picks it's not at the end of one of my animations so I'll just ban him to pick anything
from the frame range minus 30 so it doesn't it cannot play any cannot pick something that is 30
frames before the end of the animation. So basically the last second of the animation is gone.
That's what I'm doing here all the time because my takes are really big. So if I discard one second
of each of those, it's not a big deal. And that gives you the best frame of animations. And so I
can set to the system. Now it's time to play that frames. And what I do is I tell him to play the
next frame why is because I don't have any delta time I'm playing at 30 frame per second in my system
here so this feature query vector pick the best matching animation now I need to play the animation
so I tell him go play the next frame of the one you matched and that's why if you have the query
vector now if I re-picked the same feature normalized and nothing changed in my input.
I have really high, nearly 100% chance that it would pick
the correct frame. It will go back to the next frame and so it would play the next frame. This
one will re-pick the same frame, that one will go back and play the next frame and so on and so on.
So, that's one of the ways to stabilize that kind of stuff also.
Just making sure that every frame it picks the next frame.
There is also the way of saying that you don't want to play, that you don't want to compute
the search database every frame.
If your input hasn't changed, your trajectory was correctly computed.
I mean, for a bunch of frames, you know that it will just say play the next frame.
You don't need to do that search every time.
You could say, if the input doesn't change,
recompute the search to the database every X-frames.
I haven't gone that far.
I'm just recomputing every frame.
So, and then we play the animations
and we could see what happens.
So,
da, da, da, da.
In idle, of course, I don't have any data for idle.
So there he goes nuts.
But as soon as you go motions, you
could see that he start to pick the animations he prefers.
And we can see every time you pick
the different animations right now.
It pops, it pops.
But it does map, you see, align the position,
the future position there.
The yellow is what I'm computing.
And the black is the best animation
is found to match my request.
And it follows different orientations if we want.
You can switch and you get a bunch of animations.
Now, of course, it pops all the time.
So the first thing that we want to do
is to make sure that all that popping disappear
and that we can have something smooth.
And that's what I have here when I activate the inertialize.
So your initializations is also an algorithm
that has been quite popular lately.
It's basically the way of saying that
instead of trying to blend animations together,
We will tell that we have a stream of motion,
which is what we have here.
And then every time we have a big discontinuity,
so every time you pick the different animations,
you compute the offsets, the amount of error
that you have between the old animations,
the old frame, and the new frame of animations.
That give you an error, and then you will try to,
So you will add that error on top of your current frame, and then you will slowly
dampen down the amount of error correction you do.
So basically, you have a discontinuity, you compute the offsets between the discontinuity
and the old animations, and then you slow down, you slowly remove the amount of error
you had between the two.
way the initializations work it's what we have here. In this case thanks to Daniel Alden again
and the way he developed the the spring we could use the spring to also reduce the error using
a spring. So basically you said how much error I have right now and then I need in 0.2 seconds to
reduce that error to zero and using a spring it would also take into account what was the
velocities and angular velocity of your character so you're making sure that if you had a motion
that was doing this you know it will keep the accelerations and it will not just stop and go
down it will just keep that same motion thanks to the fact that the damper would take into account
the velocities of each bone. So that's why we had computed the actual bone velocities and bone
angular velocities of our animation. It's to be plugged into the initialize. So if you character
moves in one direction, it keeps the same motions and they start to blend without any abrupt change.
and that's because the spring use again the position and velocities.
So in this case the positions becomes the amount of error between the two pose and the velocities
is the direction in which the bones was going. So was it going in the right direction to remove
that error? Was it going the wrong directions to remove that error and that kind of stuff?
that damper works properly to reduce the amount of error to zeros and keep the the velocities.
And so we initialize this every time we have a discontinuity. So basically every time we don't
play the next frame we're expecting, we compute the amount of error that led to and then every frame
we just let the spring remove the arrow slowly.
And that gives us what we have here.
Now, you could play with the velocities
and how much, how quickly you want to change the values
and that kind of stuff.
For instance, right now it's fairly,
the accelerations is kind of human when you accelerate,
but it slowly stops.
I can, for instance, change the else time
when I'm releasing my pad, so it stops faster.
That's a fast stop, but everything else is still the same.
And finally, the last thing you could do
when you talk about motion matching,
but even in animation in general,
is that I have,
the red is what I'm computing,
What I want to compute, right, is the velocities I computed through my simulation.
And my character tries to follow that.
What happens is at this point you see I have a code versus animations, which are to zero,
which means that the animation plays.
And then when I finish playing the animations, I realign my simulations to where the character
is.
Right now, it means that even if I ask the animation to do,
if my simulations ask me to do something,
the animation is not doing it,
it's the animation that wins.
You could have the exact opposite,
which means that right now,
the red is what I'm computing with my spring,
and the animations try to address that,
and if it doesn't manage to match,
it slides and come back to exactly,
it realigns where my simulation is.
And you could blend between the two worlds.
In this case, I kind of match the velocities, accelerations.
There, it slides here.
But it kind of match what we want.
For instance, if I accelerate too much,
that does not exist inside of my database.
You could see that my character is sliding
like crazy trying to catch up my simulation.
And if I do the opposite, no matter what I'm asking the system,
it only does what it found inside the animation, right?
So I can go back to the proper values.
And you could do in between, for instance.
Now, what we've done so far is that's building the database,
building the feature vector, matching the feature vectors,
but we've given the same importance to everything.
I don't have a foot IK, so I'm not locking the foot on the ground right now, I'm just
playing animation.
So sometimes it does slide when it blends because of the initializations, but it's kind
of okay.
So everything now matches with the same score, everything has the same importance, all the
feature vectors have the exact same importance.
We might need or want to tweak a little what is more important inside our feature vector.
We might want to give more importance to some stuff.
So what we need to do is that we need to weight the feature vector.
Say all of my features might have a different weight.
So what we need to do is that to multiply every of the values by the weights we want
to associate them when we compute the Euclidean distance.
But what we can do instead is realizing
that if we have the weights here
when we were computing the normalized feature vector,
we can move our weights down here
and divide our standard deviations by the weights.
And if we do this, basically it means
that now we have standard deviations
that take into account the weighted importance
we want to give to everything.
And that means that nothing changed mathematically after.
So if we just basically scale the standard deviations,
the Euclidean distance, all the algorithm to do the search
stays the same, except that now it takes
into account the weights.
So what I can do is this, I can have a weight saying
that my hips velocity is important
because I want to have some continuity inside of my motion.
My feet position might not be that important,
especially if I have a foot locking system.
But the velocity is important,
so I need to make sure that I don't pick animations
that have the feet that doesn't go in the right positions.
And I can give some importance to future trajectories,
but more importance to future orientation.
And I give it discount factor for the features every time.
And then what we have now is that I divide my future standard deviations by the weights
and I renormalize and if I do this now, all the weights are encoded in that one and encoded
by that one so I don't have to change anything here, I can keep playing, except that now
it uses the weights, giving more importance to the future orientation than positions,
more importance to feed velocities than feed positions and you can play with those as you want.
We get a bunch of different values.
Now that's in a nutshell, exactly motion matching, at least when you want to do motion matching
for locomotion.
But there is another point that I want to talk and that I will do in a different video
which is the link between what motion matching is compared to reinforcement learning.
Really in a nutshell, what we could see is that we have our current pools and trajectories
and velocities and future trajectory.
So this is a Markov decision process.
There is no difference from this process to anything else.
And on top of this, if you've followed the reinforcement learning, the way I've discarded
the future values should ring a bell on how Bellman equations and reinforcement learning
works.
It's exactly the same way it's used here.
That's what reinforcement learning would have done.
So that would be for another video when I will dig a little deeper between the relations
with motion matching and reinforcement learning and why I wasn't sure if I had to put this
video inside of the reinforcement learning series, but the next one will probably be.
I hope you liked it and see you next time.